<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <info>
    <title>The Hypernumbers GUI Builder</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Gordon</firstname><surname>Guthrie</surname>
      <para>gordon [AT] hypernumbers [DOT] com</para>
    </author>
    <copyright><year>2009</year><holder>Hypernumbers Ltd</holder></copyright>
  </info>
  <preface>
    <title>Foreword</title>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para><emphasis>The Hypernumbers GUI Builder</emphasis> is aimed at the average software developer who wishes to build tools for normal people to use to build hypernumbers applications.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Purpose</title>
      <para>The purpose of this document is to:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>explain how the existing hypernumbers GUI builder works</listitem>
        <listitem>show how layouts, elements and widgets are implemented in it</listitem>
      <listitem>enable developers to write and deploy custom components for their users</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Scope</title>
    <para>This document will cover the following things:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>how existing hypernumbers GUI's work</listitem>
      <listitem>how the GUI Builder works</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>This document will <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> cover the following things:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>writing server-side functions</listitem>
      <listitem>deploying GUI's on the server</listitem>
      <listitem>storing information under your own attributes on a hypernumber</listitem>
      <listitem>modifying or extending the hypernumbers open source Javascript libraries</listitem>
      <listitem>building your own GUI framework using the raw hypernumbers server JSON API</listitem>
      <listitem>the JQuery library which hypernumbers uses 'under the covers'</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Who Is This Document <emphasis>Not</emphasis> For</title>
    <para>This is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a document for non-technical people - you need to be a programmer. If you are a basic Excel user who wants to build things with hypernumbers <emphasis>this is not for you</emphasis>. It is a technical document.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Who Is This Document For</title>
    <para>This is a document for <emphasis>software developers</emphasis> who wish to build tools for users to use with a hypernumbers server. These tools should be aimed at non-technical people - <emphasis>enabling them to build applications in the normal hypernumbers way</emphasis>. It is aimed at the generalist and not the Javascript Guru.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Contents Of This Document</title>
    <table cellpadding="5" label="Chapter Descriptions">
      <thead>
        <tr valign="top" align="center"><td>Chapter</td><td>Description</td></tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr valign="top"><td>Your Development Environment</td><td>outlines how to set up your development enironment and can be skipped by experienced javascript developers.</td></tr>
        <tr valign="top"><td>How Hypernumers GUI's work</td><td>shows how hypernumbers are bound to to the gui and describes how the GUI model works.</td></tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <note>More sections to follow!</note>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Licensing</title>
    <para>This document is release under the Creative Commons License</para>
    <para>All source code examples are available for download and are released under the Modified BSD license</para>
  </sect1>

</preface>

<chapter>
  <title>Your Development Environment</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>This chapter will explain how to set your machine up to develop GUI's for hypernumbers. It will:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>focus on the Firefox broswer (suitable for Windows, Mac, Linux and other Unix development platforms)</listitem>
      <listitem>show which plug-ins are most useful for hypernumbers GUI developers</listitem>
      <listitem>provide a brief overview of Javascript debugging tools and techniques</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <note>If you are a Javascript Guru and happy with, for instance, the Safari development environment feel free to ignore this section and do yer own thang...</note>
    <note>This is not a javascript tutorial or a detailed exposition of debugging Javascript programmes.</note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring Firefox</title>
    <para>hypernumbers needs Firefox 3 or above which can be obtained from <link xlink:href="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/upgrade.html">http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/upgrade.html</link> .</para>
    <para>You should install the following plug-ins:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Firebug</listitem>
      <listitem>JSONView</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Firebug</title>
      <para>which can be installed from <link xlink:href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/">https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/</link></para>
      <para>Firebug enables you to trace hypernumbers AJAX calls and inspect the DOM to follow what is going on.</para>
      <para>This screenshot shows us inspecting the background Ajax calls of the main hypernumbers spreadsheet GUI:</para>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/firebug1.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <para>This screenshot shows us inspecting the DOM of the main hypernumbers spreadsheet GUI:</para>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/firebug2.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <para>As we go on we will see these options being used to debug our application as we build it.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>JSONView</title>
      <para>JSONView just allows you to inspect JSON in the browser without having to save it as a file. The hypernumbers server speaks JSON exclusively so it is handy to be able to just peek at it as and when. This screenshot shows some JSON in the browser using JSONView:</para>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/jsonview.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
  
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Title</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>This chapter will
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem></listitem>
      <listitem></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <note>Note</note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Section Title</title>
    <para>Paragraph</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Subsection Title 1</title>
      <para>Para</para>
      <para>Para</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Subsection Title 2</title>
      <para>Para</para>
      <para>Para</para>
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
</chapter>


</book>
