<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<news>
    <post><title>Developers Meetup</title>
        <date>18th November, 07</date>
        <user>Dale Harvey</user>
        <text><p>During the alpha developers release of hypernumbers
                we are looking for discussion with developers that are interested in the new
                platform.<br /><br />
                On tuesday the 20th(this week) we will be hosting a developers meetup at the 
                erlang training and consulting offices (<a
                                                          href="http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=E1+6EL,+London&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;om=1&amp;ll=51.516915,-0.077248&amp;spn=0.040005,0.080338&amp;z=14">map
                    here</a>) at 6:30pm.<br /><br />
                We will do a quick presentation of the work so far, then it will be open
                discussion on what developers would expect from the platform, and applications
                they would like to write using it. Afterwards Im sure a few people will be
                along for a few drinks and more discussion.<br /><br />
                If you are interested in attending, give Gordon a quick email at
                gordon@hypernumbers.com, and this is an open invitation so invite anyone who
                might be interested, its not erlang specific so if you are into any flavour of
                development come along.<br /><br />See you on Tuesday!</p></text></post>
    
    <post>
        <title>...Something Completely Different</title>
        <date>16 November, 07</date>
        <user>Gordon Guthrie</user>
        <text><p>As if being in <a href="http://seedcamp.com">Seedcamp</a> wasn't bad enough, I have just released my book <a href="http://computerisationofadministrativelegislation.com">No Skirl Without The Drone - The Computerisation Of Administrative Legislation</a> in draft form. A must for all fans of public sector transformation</p>
            
        </text>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Erlang User Conference</title>
        <date>16 November, 07</date>
        <user>Gordon Guthrie</user>
        <text><p>Our presentation at EUC is now available online with the rest of the <a href="http://www.erlang.se/euc/07/">conference proceedings</a>. As always it was a pleasure to be in Stockholm and the conference was great. See you next year!</p>
            
        </text>
    </post>
    <post>
        <title>Welcome to HyperNumbers</title>
        <date>7 November, 07</date>
        <user>Dale Harvey</user>
        <text>
            
            <p>Welcome to the launch of hypernumbers.com! The site will mainly
                be used to keep people up to date with the progress of Hypernumbers
                and keep in touch with 3rd party developers, if you feel anything is
                missing, you can <a href="/contact/">contact us here</a>.
                <br /><br /> We are
                currently looking forward to the <a href="http://www.erlang.se/euc/07/">erlang users conference</a>
                in Stockholm tommorrow, particularly the talk on <i>Integrating OTP
                    with the Enterprise Service Bus</i> by Leslaw Lopacki. We will also be
                presenting a talk title <i>Developing RESTful Platforms with Erlang
                    and Adobe Flex</i>.</p>
        </text>
        
    </post>
</news>
